Guide to the Robert L. Patten literary papers, 1963-2014 MS 376
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Robert L. Patten literary papers
1963-2014
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Patten, Robert L.
MS 376
22 Linear Feet (22 boxes)
These Papers represent a portion of the literary career of Dr. Robert L. Patten of Rice University. His writings reflect his interests in Victorian graphic art, history of 19th century publishing, and renowned author Charles Dickens along with renowned illustrator George Cruikshank. Formats include drafts, notes and correspondence related to Dr. Patten's books, articles, lectures and reviews.
Biographical/Historical note
Robert L. Patten, the Lynette S. Autrey Professor of Humanities at Rice University, was born on April 26, 1939 in Oklahoma City. He received his B.A. from Swarthmore College in 1960. He went on to earn an M.A. (1962) and Ph.D. (1965) from Princeton University. After college, Patten lectured in English at Bryn Mawr College, leaving there in 1969 to take a position as Assistant Professor in the English Department at Rice University, where he became a full professor in 1976. In 1991 and 1992 Patten chaired Rice's English Department. The author of dozens of articles and reviews on nineteenth-century British literature, Patten used the materials in this collection to write a two-volume biography of George Cruikshank, entitled George Cruikshank's Life, Times, and Art (vol. 1, 1992; vol. 2, 1996). In 1999 The Guardian, a British newspaper, called Patten's biography one of the best books of the 1990s. Robert L. Patten was a Fulbright Scholar from 1963 to 1964 and a Guggenheim Fellow in 1980. He was also chosen as a Couper Scholar in 2004, served as president of the Rice University Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa from 1991 to 1994 and 1997 to 2002, and chaired the Dickens Society in 1973 and 1974. Patten has served in numerous capacities at Rice University, including the Sallyport Award Committee (1986-87), the Advisory Committee on Parking (1992-94), and the University Review Board (1982-84). In addition to George Cruikshank's Life, Times, and Art, Patten is the author of Charles Dickens and His Publishers(1978), and editor of George Cruikshank: A Revaluation(1974) and Literature in the Marketplace: Nineteenth-Century British Publishing and Reading Practices (1995). He also serves as editor of Studies in English Literature and founded and briefly edited the periodical Dickens Studies Newsletter.
Scope and Contents note
These papers represent a portion of the literary career of Dr. Robert L. Patten of Rice Unviersity. His writings reflect his interests in Victorian graphic art, history of 19th century publishing, and renowned author Charles Dickens along with renowned illustrator George Cruikshank. Formats include drafts, notes and correspondence related to Dr. Patten's books, articles, lectures and reviews.
Conditions Governing Access Note
This material is open for research. Permission to publish material from the Robert L. Patten Literary papers must be obtained from the Woodson research Center, Fondren Library.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Accruals Note
Materials are expected to be added to this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
The collection was a gift donated by Dr. Robert L. Patten March 16, 1999.
Related Materials
Robert L. Patten: George Cruikshank research materials http://library.rice.edu/collections/WRC/finding-aids/manuscripts/0493.
Rice University Master of Graduate House records (Bob Patten) http://library.rice.edu/collections/WRC/finding-aids/manuscripts/gradstudentmaster.
Studies in English Literature 1500-1900 records, 1959-2003 http://library.rice.edu/collections/WRC/finding-aids/university-archives/SEL-1500-1900-records.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; 16th- 19th century English literature; Nineteenth century; Literature
Document Types
papers (document genres)
Subjects (Persons)
Dickens, Charles; Cruikshank, George
- Series I: Books, 1963-1996, 58782
  - Subseries A: Pickwick Papers, 58788
    - Note cards on characters in Pickwick Papers, 58793 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Personal notes for Pickwick edition: Dedication-XLVII, 58794 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Pickwick note cards, 58795 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Explanatory note cards for Pickwick Papers p. 1-275, 58796 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Explanatory note cards for Pickwick Papers p. 280-594, 58797 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Explanatory note cards for Pickwick Papers p. 597-801, 58798 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Explanatory chapter notes on Dicken's Pickwick Papers, 58799 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Pickwick notes, 1963-1964; 58800 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Pickwick introduction annotated draft, 58801 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Pickwick final draft, 1963-1964; 58802 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Appendices to Penguin Pickwick, 58803 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Pickwick Papers publisher's proof copy: Title- Ch. XX, 58804 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Pickwick Papers publisher's proof copy: Ch. XXI-XLIII, 58805 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Pickwick Papers publisher's proof copy: Ch. XLIV- Appendix B, 58806 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Penguin Books completed publication of Pickwick Papers, 1972; 58807 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Pickwick scholarship, 1972-1979; 58808 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Subseries B: George Cruikshank; A Revaluation, 58789
    - Cruikshank note cards, 58809 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Cruikshank: The Artist and the Author, 1872; 58810 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Scholarship and correspondence: Princeton librarians, 1970-1978; 58811 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Bradburn, 1971-1972; 58812 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Burton, 1972-1974; 58813 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Feaver, 1972-1974; 58814 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Fowles, 1971-1973; 58815 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Hemstedt, 1972; 58816 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Harvey, 1971-1974; 58817 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: James, 1972-1974; 58818 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Johnson, 1970-1972; 58819 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Kunzle, 1972-1977; 58820 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Levine, 1971-1972; 58821 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Paulson, 1972-1974; 58822 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Searle, 1972-1974; 58823 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Steig, 1971-1974; 58824 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Stone, 1971-1974; 58825 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: Vogler, 1971-1974; 58826 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Cruikshank correspondence: rejects/na, 1970-1972; 58827 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Cruikshank communications from Robert L. Patten, 1972-1973; 58828 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Illustrations, 1973; 58829 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Cruikshank organization, 58830 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Contributor notes, 58831 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
    - Princeton University Library Chronicle publication, 1973-1974; 58832 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Comments on the Cruikshank volume, June 1974; 58833 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - George Cruikshank illustrations, 58834 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    - George Cruikshank alumni talk slides, March 1980; 58835 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - George Cruikshank: A Revaluation page proofs, 58836 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
    - George Cruikshank: A Revaluation reissue, 1992; 58837 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Subseries C: Charles Dickens and his publishers, 58790
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: replies to copy editor, 58838 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: correspondence, 58839 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: correspondence with Clarendon Press Oxford, 58840 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: correspondence with Jean, 58841 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: Rosenbach Foundation Museum, 58842 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: addenda for second edition, 58843 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: permissions, 58844 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: financial notes and appendices notes, 58845 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: B&E records, 58846 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: B&E records, 167425 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: illustrations, 58847 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: introduction, 58848 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter one, "The Professional Author", 58849 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter two, "Boz and Macrone", 58850 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter three note cards, 58851 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter three drafts and notes, 58852 (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter three, "Pickwick Papters" MSS and illustrations, 58853 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter four note cards, 58854 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter four, "Dickens and the Burlington Street Brigade", 58855 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter five note cards, 58856 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter five, "'The Best of Publishers, Past, Present, or to Come'", 58857 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter six, "Master Humphrey's clock: 'wind, wind, wind'", 58858 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter seven, "Trouble in Eden: American Notes and Martin", 58859 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter eight, "The Break", 58860 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter nine, 58861 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter ten note cards, 58862 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter ten, "Dombey and Son, 'the greates success'", 58863 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter eleven note cards, 58864 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter eleve, "David Copperfield and the Cheap Edition", 58865 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter twelve note cards, 58866 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter twelve, "Bleak House", 58867 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter thirteen note cards, 58868 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter thirteen "Working the Copyrights", 58869 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter thirteen final corrected copy, 58870 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter thirteen as prospectus, 58871 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter fourteen note cards, 58872 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter fourteen, "Return to Chapman and Hall", 58873 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter fifteen note cards, 58874 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter fifteen, "The End", 58875 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter fifteen final copy, 58876 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter sixteen, "The Audience Widens", 58877 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: chapter sixteen final copies, 58878 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: appendices, 58879 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: references, 58880 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: misc. articles, 58881 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: references (A-L), 58882 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: references (M-Z), 58883 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: note cards and references (A-C), 58884 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: note cards and references (D-G), 58885 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: note cards and references (H-O), 58886 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: note cards and references (P-Z), 58887 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: microfilm, 58888 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: Contts account financial records, 58889 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: styling book, includes "The Bantam Story: Twenty-Five Years of Paperback Publishing" by Clarence Peterson, 58890 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: footnote proof readings, 58891 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: prefaces and typescript, 58892 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: miscellaneous, 58893 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: financial records concerning sales of Dickens literary works, 58894 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: photocopy of manuscript, 58895 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: typescript sent to publishers, 58896 (Box 9, Folder 2-6)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: reviews, 58897 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: typescript returned from publishers, 58898 (Box 9, Folder 8-13)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: page proofs, 58899 (Box 10, Folder 1-6)
    - Charles Dickens and his publishers: reissue, 1990; 58900 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Subseries D: George Cruikshank's life, times and art, 58791
    - George Cruikshank's life, times and art: volume one: 1792-1835, finalized version of all essays, 58901 (Box 10, Folder 8-12)
    - George Cruikshank's life, times and art: volume one: 1792-1835, book proof, 58902 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - George Cruikshank's life, times and art: volume one: 1792-1835, book proof, 167426 (Box 11, Folder 1-5)
  - Subseries E: Literature in the marketplace: nineteenth-century British publishing and reading practices, 58792
    - Cambridge University Press, 1994-1996; 58903 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Dickens Project correspondence, 1991-1993; 58904 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Preface, 58905 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Simon Eliot essay, 58906 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Peter Manning essay, 58907 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Stephen Gill essay, 58908 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Hillis Miller essay, 58909 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Robert L. Patten essay, 58910 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Linda Huges/ Mike Lund essay, 58911 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Kelly Mays essay, 58912 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Jonathan Rose essay, 58913 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Gerard Curtis essay, 58914 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Catherine Judd essay, 58915 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Catherine Robson essay, 58916 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Maura Ives essay, 58917 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Laurel Brake essay, 58918 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Elizabeth Morrison essay, 58919 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Literature in the Marketplace: finalized versions of all essays, 58920 (Box 12, Folder 1-4)
    - Literature in the Marketplace: book proof, 58921 (Box 12, Folder 5-10)
- Series II: Articles, 1964-1990, 58783
  - "The Interpolated Tales in Pickwick Papers" for Dickens Studies, 1964; 58922 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - "The Art of Pickwick's Interpolated Tales" for ELH, 1967; 58923 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - "The Unpropitious Muse and Pickwick's Interpolated Tales" for Dickens Studies, 1967-1969; 58924 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - "Boz, Phiz, and Pickwick in the Pound" for ELH, 58925 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - "The Sales of Dickens' Works" for The Critical Heritage: Charles Dickens, 1968; 58926 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - "Portraits of Pott: Lord Brougham and The Pickwick Papers", 1968-1969; 58927 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - "Capitalism and Compassion in Oliver Twist" for Studies in the Novel, 1969; 58928 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - "The Story-weaver at his Loom: Dickens and the Beginning of The Old Curiosity Shop" for Dickens the Craftsman, 1969-1970; 58929 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - "A Surprising Transformation: Dickens, Nature and the City", 1970s; 58930 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - "The Fight at the Top of the Tree: Vanity Fair vs. Dombey and Son" for SEL, 1970; 58931 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - "Portraits of Pott: Lord Brougham and The Pickwick Papers" for The Dickensian, 1970; 58932 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - "A Surprising Transformation: Dickens, Nature, and the Hearth" for Nature and the Victorian Imagination, 1972-1977; 58933 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - "Pickwick Papers and the Discovery of Serial Fiction" for Rice University Studies, August 30, 1974; 58934 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - "Autobiography into Autobiography: The Evolution of David Copperfield" for Approaches to Victorian Autobiography, 1975-1978; 58935 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Article on Pickwick payments, 1976; 58936 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Dickens' Second American Tour…, 1976-1978; 58937 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - "Conventions of Georgian Caricature" for Art Journal, 1983; 58938 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - "Reviewing Reviewing: From the Editor's Desk" for Literary Reviewing for a Scholarly Audience, 1984; 58939 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - "I thought of Mr. Pickwick, and wrote the first number" for Dickens Quarterly, 1985; 58940 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - "George Cruikshank's Grimm Humor" for Phantasie am langen Zügel, 1985-1987; 58941 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - "Taking a Walk; or Setting Forth from Gateshead" for Approaches to Teaching Jane Eyre, 1989-1991; 58942 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - "George Cruikshank's Private Day Book, 1810-1825" for Princeton University Library Chronicle, 58943 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - "Waltzing with Witches" for Review of Contemporary Fiction, 1990; 58944 (Box 13, Folder 23)
- Series III: Lectures, 1984-1992, 58784
  - "Dickens: Doubles: Twain: Twins" for Nineteenth Century Fiction, 1984-1985; 58945 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - "In Search of Cruikshank" for Swarthmore College Bulletin, 1992; 58946 (Box 13, Folder 25)
- Series IV: Brief Reviews by Patten, 1966-1997, 58785
  - Review of Circle of Fire…for Dickens and the Twentieth Century, 1966; 58947 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - "So Much Pains about the Chalk-Faced Kid" for Dickens Studies, 1967; 58948 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Review of "Putting Quilp to Rest" for Victorian Society Newsletter, 1969; 58949 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Review of "The Serpent" (Rice Players), 1971; 58950 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Review of The Old Curiosity Shop for The Dickensian, 1972; 58951 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Review of The Anatomy of College English for AAUP Review, 1973; 58952 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Review of Trollope: His Life and Art, 1975; 58953 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Review of Oscar Wilde: A Biography, 1976; 58954 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Review of Charles Dickens, The Public Readings for Nineteenth Century Fiction, 1976; 58955 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Review of Until the Colors Fade, 1977; 58956 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Review of Dickens' Apprentice Years: The Making of a Novelist, 1977; 58957 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Review of Victorian Novelists and Publishers for Analytical and Enumerative Bibliography, 1977; 58958 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Review of Charles Dickens: His Tragedy and Triumph, 1977; 58959 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Review of The Triumph of the Novel…for The Dickensian, 1978; 58960 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Review of The Dickens Myth: Its Genius and Structure for Novel: A Forum on Fiction, 1979; 58961 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Review of Dickens: A Life, 1979; 58962 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Review of Dickens and Charity for American Historical Review, 1979; 58963 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Review of Steig and Buchanan books for Nineteenth Century Fiction, 1979; 58964 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Review of numerous books for Review, 1980; 58965 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Review of Cohen and Vogler books for Nineteenth Century Fiction, 1981; 58966 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Review of painting books for Victorian Studies, 1981; 58967 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Review of Charles Dickens in the Original Cloth for American Book Collector, 1982; 58968 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Review of Jerome Charyn: Artist as Mytholept for Novel: A Forum on Fiction, 1983; 58969 (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Review of Charles Dickens in the Original Cloth for Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America, 1984; 58970 (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Review of Kaplan and Davies for Dickens Studies Newsletter, 1985; 58971 (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - Review of The Images of the Middle Ages in Romantic and Victorian Literature for American Historical Review, 1986; 58972 (Box 14, Folder 26)
  - Review of Schlicke and Timko et.al. books for Victorian Studies, 1987; 58973 (Box 14, Folder 27)
  - Review of The Common Writer: Life in Nineteenth Century Grub Street for Review, 1987; 58974 (Box 14, Folder 28)
  - Review of The History of the Comic Strip, Vol.2 for Print Quarterly, 1991; 58975 (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - Review of The Printed Image and the Transformation of Popular Culture for American Historical Review, 1993; 58976 (Box 14, Folder 30)
  - Review of Authors and Owners: The Invention of Copyright for Sharp, 1994-1995; 58977 (Box 14, Folder 31)
  - Review of The Dent Uniform Edition of Dickens' Journalism for ANQ, 1995; 58978 (Box 14, Folder 32)
  - Review of Some Patterns and Trends in British Publishing for PBSA, 1995; 58979 (Box 14, Folder 33)
  - Review of Radical Satire and Print Culture for JEGP, 1996; 58980 (Box 14, Folder 34)
  - Review of Victorian Fiction: Writers, Publishers, Readers for Studies in the Novel, 1996; 58981 (Box 14, Folder 35)
  - Review of The Age of Caricature... for American Historical Review, 1997; 58982 (Box 14, Folder 36)
- Series V: Review Articles by Patten, 1970-1984, 58786
  - Oliver Twist paperbacks review, 1970s, 58983 (Box 14, Folder 37)
  - Review of The Victorian City: Images and Realities, 1975; 58984 (Box 14, Folder 38)
  - Review of Dickens bibliographies for Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America, 1983; 58985 (Box 14, Folder 39)
  - "Recent Dickens Studies: 1982" for Dickens Studies Annual, 1984; 58986 (Box 14, Folder 40)
- Series VI: General notecards and fragments, 1964-1993, 58787
  - The Old Curiosity Shop notes, May 1964; 58987 (Box 14, Folder 41)
  - David Copperfield edition for Bantam Books, Inc., 1967; 58988 (Box 14, Folder 42)
  - The Ruined Garden: Studies in the Imagination of Charles Dickens, 1968; 58989 (Box 14, Folder 43)
  - "Dickens Time and Again", 1970; 58990 (Box 14, Folder 44)
  - "This Gift of Transferred Life" for Times Literary Supplement, 1980; 58991 (Box 14, Folder 45)
  - Report on Dickens' Working Notes for His Novels, 1982; 58992 (Box 14, Folder 46)
  - "Charles Dickens and Serial Publications" for FIPSE, 1987; 58993 (Box 14, Folder 47)
  - Report on Institution and the Individual Talent: The Commodity Text in Nineteenth Century England, 1992; 58994 (Box 14, Folder 48)
  - "The Canon and the Sophomore Survey" for Handbook of College Teaching, 1992-1993; 58995 (Box 14, Folder 49)
  - Note cards on Dickens' various works, 58996 (Box 15)
- Series VII: Oversize items, 156241
  - Cruikshank items separated from box 8 (Box 16)
- Series VIII: Book, Charles Dickens and 'Boz': the birth of the industrial-age author
  General
  Published 2012.
  - Introduction (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Chapter 1 (Box 17, Folder 2-4)
  - Chapter 2 (Box 17, Folder 5-8)
  - Chapter 3 (Box 17, Folder 9-11)
  - Chapter 4 (Box 17, Folder 12-14)